A Guide to the James Madison University Commencement Programs, 1910-2019: UA 0050
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
James Madison University Commencement Programs,
1910-2019
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
James Madison University
UA 0050
1.6 cubic feet; 4 boxes
The James Madison University Commencement Programs, 1910-2019, consist of four boxes (1.6 cubic feet) of commencement programs and supplementary materials for graduation ceremonies held at James Madison University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Commencement programs have been collected from multiple sources over time, including official university affiliates and alumni collections.
Accruals
The most recent commencement programs are added to this collection every semester.
Bio/Historical Note
The first commencement program at the State Normal School for Women was held from June 7-14, 1910, as the first commencement programs were held over a period of days with events spread out over the course of the ceremony. The first commencement program began with a play by the senior class, continued throughout the week with a recital by the music department, commencement services and sermons led by local clergy, and ended with an address by the then-governor of Virginia William Hodges Mann and the presentation of diplomas by Samuel P. Duke at the local courthouse assembly hall.
In subsequent years, the commencement ceremonies followed a similar format (a sermon on the first day, activities in the subsequent days, and diplomas handed out on the final day) over a shorter span of time. For a period of time, all events took place during a single day, until 2011 when commencement ceremonies were held over the course of multiple days during the first weekend of May. All commencement ceremonies that follow 2011 adhere to this three-day format: the Graduate School commencement occurs on the first day, the University Program commencement begins the second day ceremonies, and College/Departmental commencement programs occur on the second and third day. These ceremonies take place in a variety of locations on campus, including the Quadrangle, Bridgeforth Stadium, the lawn of Duke Hall, Alumni Centennial Park, and the Festival Ballroom.
Scope and Content
The James Madison University Commencement Programs, 1910-2019, consist of four boxes (1.6 cubic feet) of commencement programs and supplementary materials for graduation ceremonies held at James Madison University. Some items of note include programs from the very first commencement ceremony held by the university when it was still a State Normal School and programs from the 2019 Nursing School Spring commencement ceremony.
Commencement programs typically document graduates' names, their major or program of study, students graduating with honors, other honors and awards, and speakers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
State Normal and Industrial School for Women (Harrisonburg, Va.); State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.); State Teachers College at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.); Madison College; James Madison University; Commencement ceremonies
Genre and Form Terms:
Programs (documents)
- Commencement Programs, 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Commencement Programs, 1921-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Commencement Programs, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Commencement Programs, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Commencement Programs, 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Commencement Programs, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Commencement Programs, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Commencement Programs, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Commencement Programs, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Commencement Programs, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Commencement Programs, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Commencement Programs, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Commencement Programs, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Commencement Programs, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Commencement Programs, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Commencement Programs, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Commencement Programs, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Commencement Programs, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Commencement Programs, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Commencement Programs, 2009-2011 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Commencement Programs, 2012-2013 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Commencement Programs, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Commencement Programs, 2016-May 2018 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Commencement Programs, December 2018-2019 (Box 4, Folder 5)